Guide to the Mildred Miller Posvar Papers, 1939-2008 CTC.2009.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mildred Miller Posvar Papers
1939-2008
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Miller, Mildred
CTC.2009.01
15 Linear Feet (23 boxes and 15 scrapbooks)
Mildred Miller Posvar was a star performer at the Metropolitan Opera from 1951 to 1974 and the wife of Wesley Posvar, the fifteenth Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh. The Mildred Miller Posvar Papers are a mixed media collection primarily documenting her performing career at the Met. The materials also cover her training at the New England Conservatory of Music, her position as the First Lady of the University of Pittsburgh, and her involvement in the Opera Theatre of Pittsburgh. The collection includes compact discs, video tapes, newspaper and magazine clippings, programs, photographs, scrapbooks, and correspondence.
Previous Citation
Mildred Miller Posvar Papers, 1939-2008, CTC.2009.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mildred Miller Posvar in 1978, June 2009, and September 2013.
Scope and Content Notes
The Mildred Miller Posvar Papers are arranged into seven series. The single largest portion of the collection is the audio recordings. These recordings were on cassette tapes, reel to reel, and vinyl records. Since the donation, they have been transferred to compact discs. Other items in the collection include photographs, programs, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, and a small amount of correspondence. The majority of the materials focus on her performing career, however there are some items that relate to her position as the University's First Lady and her involvement in the Opera Theatre of Pittsburgh.
Biography
Mildred Miller Posvar, known professionally as Mildred Miller, is a classical mezzo-soprano who had a career performing in operas, concerts, and recitals beginning in the 1940's. She made her opera debut in 1946 at the Tanglewood Music Festival. She was a principal artist at the Metropolitan Opera in New York from 1951 through 1974. In 1978 she founded the Opera Theater of Pittsburgh and served as its Artistic Director until 1999. She taught music and voice first at the University of Pittsburgh and presently teaches at Carnegie Mellon University. She has also taught master classes in many other institutions.
She was born Mildred Müller on December 16, 1924 in Cleveland, Ohio and attended the Cleveland Metropolitan School District graduating from West High School 1942. She entered the Cleveland Institute of Music where she was a voice student of Marie Simmelink Kraft. After graduating in 1946, she entered the New England Conservatory where she earned her Artist Diploma in 1948. After studying and performing abroad she met up with Wesley Wentz Posvar, a schoolmate from her high school in Cleveland. Wesley and Mildred were married on June 13, 1950. After her marriage, she continued to use the stage name of Mildred Miller in all matters and materials that related to her performing career.
Her 1951 debut at the Metropolitan Opera House in the role of Cherubino, in Mozart's Le nozze di Figero, began a string of 24 consecutive years of performing at the Met. Mrs. Posvar was also mentored by Lotte Lehmann (1888-1976) and became a prominent Lieder singer. She performed in Italy, Germany, Austria, Japan, the Philippines, Singapore, China, and all over the United States. She was also a frequent featured guest on radio and television shows like the Voice of Firestone, the Bell Telephone Hour, and the Ed Sullivan Show. In 1967, Wesley Posvar became the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh. During her time as First Lady of Pitt, she continued to perform at the Met and toured regularly. Mrs. Posvar also gave the first performance by a musician at the Nixon White House for the retirement of Chief Justice Earl Warren in 1969.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series:
Series I. Programs, 1944-2004
Series II. Ephemera, 1942-2008
Series III. Newspaper Clippings, 1949-2008
Series IV. Photographs, 1946-2008
Series V. Audio/Visual Recordings, 1953-1965
Series VI. Scrapbooks, 1939-1973
Series VII. Oversized Materials, 1952-1972
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Related Material
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Wesley W. Posvar, Administrative Files, 1967-1991, UA.2.10.1967-1991, University of Pittsburgh Archives, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scrapbooks; Clippings (Information artifacts); Ephemera; Photographs; Sound recordings; Audiocassettes; Audiotapes; Videocassettes; Long-playing records; University of Pittsburgh; Theater; Music; Theater programs; Opera -- New York (State) -- New York -- 20th century; Opera -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Mezzo-sopranos -- New York (State) -- New York; University of Pittsburgh -- Administration; Opera Theatre of Pittsburgh; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.); Lehmann, Lotte; Posvar, Wesley Wentz; Miller, Mildred
- Programs, 1944-2004; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The first series of this collection arranges the hundreds of concert and opera programs that were amassed over the course of Mildred Miller's career. They are filed in chronological order. Each year can have several folders, one or more folders for Metropolitan Opera programs, one for concert and recital programs, and another for non-Met opera programs. Please note that several of the early programs are in poor condition.
  - Undated programs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1944-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2-19)
  - Programs, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - Programs, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Programs, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
  - Programs, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1-9)
  - Programs, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Programs, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Programs, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 1-9)
  - Programs, 1971-1979 (Box 9, Folder 1-16)
  - Programs, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Programs, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Ephemera, 1942-2008; II.
  Within this series are miscellaneous materials including press releases, correspondence, speeches, etc. Of particular note are the materials that relate to the Mildred Miller fan club, materials from her performances on the Voice of Firestone and the Bell Telephone Hour, and printouts from the Metropolitan Opera's database that list every one of Miller's Met performances. The items are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Anniversary of Mildred Miller's Metropolitan Opera debut, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Autographed material, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bell Telephone Hour, 1952-1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bell Telephone Hour scripts, 1953-1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Biographies, 1969-1991 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Boys Will Be Girls, Girls Will Be Boys: Cross Gender Roles in Opera - SUNY Buffalo campus Music Library exhibit catalog, October 2003 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Cleveland concert transcript (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Cleveland Institute of Music, 1942-1955 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Cleveland Institute of Music - Distinguished Alumni Award, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Cleveland's West Shore Concert Series 1953-1954 calendar, 2007 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Columbia Artists Management, 1955-1961 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Commercial recordings, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1995 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Lotte Lehmann, 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Fan club, 1952-1973 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Famsworth, Clyde - unpublished article, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Franklin Square House, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Goethe celebration Pittsburgh concert, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Governor's office letter, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Invitations, 1972-1975 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Metropolitan Opera, 1952-1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Metropolitan Opera Archive materials, 1951-2008 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Metropolitan Opera Association annual report, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Mildred Miller - Complete Metropolitan Opera Performances, 1951-1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Mildred Miller - Concerts and recitals, 1952-1972 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - New England Conservatory of Music and Boris Goldovsky, 1951-2008 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Notable Women in the Arts, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Notifications of Mildred Miller's absence from performances (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Opera Theatre of Pittsburgh, 1982-1983 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Paintings, 1951-1952 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Press books and press kits, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases - Miller reviews, 1972-1985 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Promotional material, 1951-1977 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Speeches, 1978-1994 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Telegrams, 1951-1954 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Television appearances, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Voice of Firestone, 1953-1958 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - YWCA's 20th Tribute to Women, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1949-2008; III.
  In this series are newspaper and magazine clippings. There are concert reviews, advertisements, and articles on the Posvar's home life. The clippings are in chronological order.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1949-1957 (Box 14, Folder 1-12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958-1975 (Box 15, Folder 1-19)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1976-2008 (Box 16, Folder 1-10)
- Photographs, 1946-2008; IV.
  This series of photographs are arranged in alphabetical order by subject title. These photos show Mildred Miller Posvar in all of her various roles – opera star, recitalist, first lady, wife, and mother. There are several large photographs that are in the oversized materials series.
  - Ariadne auf Naxos - Composer (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Barber of Seville - Rosina, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Boris Goldovsky, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Carmen, 1947-1965 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Carousel - Aunt Hettie, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Cavalleria rusticana - Lola (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Columbus Ohio concert, March 5, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Contact sheets (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Cosi fan tutte - Dorabella (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Evening gown, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Evening gown - negatives, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Fairfax Virginia recital, October 1970 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Falstaff, 1964-1966 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Faust - Siebel, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - La forza de destino, 1951-1957 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Fyodor - Boris Goudouov (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Goethe celebration Pittsburgh concert, October 31 1982 (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Hansel and Gretel, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Headshots, 1946-1963 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Idomeneo, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Lotte Lehmann - Lieder singer, 1966-1968 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Madama Butterfly - Suzuki, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Magic Flute, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Marriage of Figaro - Cherubino, 1952-1957 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Die Meistersinger (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Merry Wives of Windsor film, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Metropolitan Opera photos, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Metropolitan Opera tours, 1948-1970s (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - New England Conservatory of Music and Boris Goldovsky, 1951-2008 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Peter Grimes, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Photo albums, 1961-1966 (Box 18, Folder 14-15)
  - Portraits (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Portraits - negatives (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Portraits in Chancellor's residence, 1967-1971 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Portraits with family, 1958-1971 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Portraits with Wesley Posvar, 1952-1980 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Publicity shots, 1951-1974 (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
  - Recital tour of Asia, 1962; This tour is also refered to as the "Oriental Recital Tour" in newspaper and magazine articles. There is one scrapbook that documents this tour in the scrapbook series. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Recitals, 1947-1984 (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
  - Recitals - negatives (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Recording shots, 1960 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Der Rosenkavalier - Annina, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Der Rosenkavalier - Octavian, 1957-1967 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Tales of Hoffman - Nicklausse, 1953 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Television photos, 1952-1963 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1971-1972 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - White House, April 23, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - World Series, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Unlabled photos (Box 21, Folder 4-5)
  - Unlabled photos - negatives (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Audio/Visual Recordings, 1953-1965; V.
  There were over 200 audio recordings that were donated to the Curtis Collection along with Mrs. Posvar's papers. A small amount of the recordings were commercially available LPs; these were added to the Music Library's circulating collection. Of the non-commercially available materials, there were vinyl records, reel to reel tapes, and cassette tapes. These recordings have been transferred onto compact discs. Each of the recordings is in the process of being cataloged individually and indexed in the University of Pittsburgh Library System's online catalog, Pittcat+. For inquires into these materials please contact Special Collections staff.
  There are also 10 VHS tapes in this series. Most of these VHS tapes are Mildred Miller's performances on the Bell Telephone Hour and Voice of Firestone television programs. Also included is a North American VHS copy of her Austrian film the Merry Wives of Windsor. They are available to be taken from the Special Collections Department Reading Room to the Stark Media Services Department on the ground floor of the Hillman Library for viewing.
  Please click here to see the audio recordings that have been cataloged and are available for use at the Music Library.
  - Audio (list of items coming soon), 1.
  - Video, 2.
    - Bell Telephone Hour, January 20 1961 (Box 22, Video 1)
    - Die lustigen Weiber von Windsor Sigma III Corp., 1965 (Box 22, Video 2)
    - Golden Voices, Silver Screen (Box 22, Video 3)
    - Metropolitan Opera documentary - segment on Mildred Miller (Box 22, Video 4)
    - Tale of Tanglewood: Peter Grimes Reborn (Box 22, Video 5)
    - Voice of Firestone, 1953-1963 (Box 22, Video 6-10)
- Scrapbooks, 1939-1973; VI.
  There are 15 scrapbooks in this series. They contain newspaper clippings, programs, and in some instances photographs. Some of the date ranges for the scrapbooks overlap and clippings are duplicated in multiple scrapbooks. For the most part, the scrapbooks center on the performing career of Mildred Miller from her days in high school through her years as a mainstay of the Metropolitan Opera. Not many of the scrapbooks have a more singular theme than that. But, there are a few that are more focused and have shorter date spans. For example the scrapbooks which cover Mildred's time in high school, her years in Colorado, and the Posvars tour of Asia. The scrapbooks are in chronological order by the first year that is covered. The majority of these scrapbooks are in fragile condition and should be handled with care.
  - Scrapbook - high school, 1939-1943 (Box 22, Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook - Cleveland Institute of Music and Tanglewood, 1943-1947 (Box 22, Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook - Cleveland Institute of Music and New England Conservatory of Music and New England Opera Theatre, 1946-1949 (Box 22, Volume 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1946-1951 (Box 22, Volume 4)
  - Scrapbooks - oversized pressbooks, 1950-1973 (Box 22, Volume 5-7)
  - Scrapbook - Colorado years, 1950-1953 (Box 22, Volume 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1951 (Box 22, Volume 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1951-1955 (Box 22, Volume 10)
  - Scrapbook - domestic life articles, 1951-1960 (Box 22, Volume 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1952-1959 (Box 22, Volume 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1957-1962 (Box 22, Volume 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1969 (Box 22, Volume 14)
  - Scrapbook - tour of Asia, 1962 (Box 22, Volume 15)
- Oversized Materials, 1952-1972; VII.
  This series contains oversized materials that include awards, photographs, and posters. Several of the photographs are matted and in folio folders.
  - Awards and proclamations, 1952-1958 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Oversized clippings and journals, 1952-1956 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Oversized portrait photographs (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Posters (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Posvar family portrait photograph (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Publicity materials for the Merry Wives of Windsor film, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Reproduction of painting of Mildred Miller (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Serge de Gastyne and Mildred Miller photograph (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - University of Pittsburgh Chancellor's residence photographs (Box 23, Folder 9)
- Addition, 1943-2002
  The contents of this series were donated by Mildred Posvar and her daughter Lisa Rossi in September 2013.
  The materials consist of newspaper clippings, recital and concert programs, performance contracts, and correspondence. Also included are Mrs. Posvar's high school yearbook and a set of items relating to her performance in honor of Chief Justice Earl Warren and Mrs. Warren at the White House, on April 23, 1969. Among the items are a thank you letter by President Richard Nixon. The contracts represent Mildred Miller's various performances during the 1950s. There are contracts for the Metropolitan Opera, radio and television appearances, Community Concerts through Columbia Artists Management, etc. Please note that there is only one contract post 1957.
  - Bowling Green State University commencement program - Mildred Miller doctor of musical arts, June 5, 1960 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Classic Record Collector - Bruno Walter article, 2001-2002 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Contracts, 1951-1957, 1991 (Box 24, Folder 3-5)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1966, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Lotte Lehmann, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Falstaff negatives - Metropolitan Opera, 1964 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Metropolitan Opera House Gala Farewell - Admission pass, April 16, 1966 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1947-1997 (Box 24, Folder 10-11)
  - Photographs (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Programs, 1953-1978 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Quotannis '43 West High School yearbook, January 1943 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Tour of Asia negatives, 1962 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Der Rosenkavalier micro-negatives - Vienna, 1963 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Der Rosenkavalier negatives (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - White House perfromance, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 18)